now let's briefly talk about Optical
discs an optical disc is very similar to
a hard dis in that it has a platter that
rotates and we store the bits on the
surface of the disc the difference is
that instead of there being a head that
needs to be placed very close to the
disk surface we can shoot a laser to
this surface and the Reflection from the
material here will tell us whether we
have a zero or a one but many of the
other properties of the optical discs
are very similar to hard diss they have
tracks and so on unlike hard drives that
tend to be closed units so you don't
just insert a new hard drive into the
machine and you don't carry one with you
usually Optical drives don't need the
laser to get that close to the surface
so the smudges or dust are less of a
problem for it basically if there is a
speck of dust here it doesn't scratch
the laser as it rotates but a speck of
dust will scratch the magnetic head as
it rotates and probably glue itself to
the head and then the head no longer
works so hard drives have much more of a
problem with dirt so they need to be in
an enclosed case because Optical discs
suffer less from this problem we often
see them in the form of CDs and DVDs
that we can carry around and even though
they get dirty we can still read data
from them but as a result of them being
portable they need to be standardized so
that we can put a CD or a DVD into any
drive that we want and the
standardization helps improve
portability and their usefulness but it
limits the rate of improvement because
the technology improves but then that
technology needs to make it through a
standards process where companies agree
that something will be a standard and
only then make it into products so so
really the technology can improve
relatively rapidly but we don't see any
of that progress until a new standard is
decided on at which point products are
released in contrast with hard drives
the whole enclosure needs to obey some
standards about how to connect to the
rest of the computer but what happens
inside the enclosure can be the latest
and greatest technology in magnetic
discs so usually Optical discs are used
for pretty much carrying the data around
storing music movies and so on